Finding Aid for Isaac Peckham Christiancy papers, 1830-1874
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Isaac Peckham Christiancy papers 1830-1874
Christiancy, Isaac Peckham, 1812-1890.
85989 mf 318c, mf 319 c
Republican State Senator from Monroe County, Michigan, 1850-1851, Michigan Supreme Court Justice, 1858-1875, U.S. Senator, 1875-1879, and U.S. Minister to Peru. Letters to his children, business letters from his law partner Robert M. McClelland, Catholic Bishop Peter P. LeFevre and Nathaniel L. Christiancy; legal documents, Civil War address, Michigan Supreme Court docket book, and miscellaneous papers.
2 microfilms 1 linear foot
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The provenance of this collection is uncertain.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Isaac Peckham Christiancy was born near Johnstown, Fulton County, N. Y., March 12, 1812. He moved to Monroe, Michigan in 1836 where he would practice law from 1838 to 1858. During this time, he would also serve as prosecuting attorney for Monroe County 1841-1846; delegate to the National Free Soil Convention at Buffalo in 1848; Free Soil candidate for Governor in 1852; and Michigan State Senator 1850-1852. In 1856, Christiancy was elected associate judge of the Michigan Supreme Court. He was twice re-elected and served until 1875 when he was elected to the United States Senate. He served until 1879 at which time President Hayes selected him to be United States Minister to Peru. He served until 1881 when he returned to practice law in Lansing, Michigan. He died September 8, 1890.
The Isaac Peckham Christiancy collection relates primarily to the period in his career prior to becoming a United States Senator and Minister to Peru. The papers have been arranged into the following series: Background Information; Correspondence; Business, financial, and miscellaneous; Legal files: law practice and Michigan Supreme Court. Of note are letters to his children and business letters from his law partner Robert M. McClelland, Catholic Bishop Peter P. LeFevre and Nathaniel L. Christiancy. In addition, there is an address he gave during the Civil War.
Subjects:
Catholic Church.; Michigan--Politics and government--1845-1860.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Monroe (Mich.); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 4th (1861-1864). Company A.; United States. Congress. Senate.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Contributors:
Christiancy, Nathaniel L.; Lefevere, Peter Paul, 1804-1869.; McClelland, Robert, 1807-1880.
- Background Information
  - Miscellaneous: include chronology of Christiancy's life, typescripts of documents in other repositories, descriptions of the collection (Reel 1)
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1840-1849 (Reel 1)
    - 1850-1851 (Reel 1)
    - 1852-1854 (Reel 1)
    - January-May 1855 (Reel 1)
    - June-December 1855 (Reel 1)
    - 1856-1861 (Reel 1)
  - Correspondence with Robert McClelland
    - 1850-1853 (Reel 1)
    - January-May 1854 (Reel 1)
    - June-December 1854 (Reel 1)
    - January-July 1855 (Reel 1)
    - August-December 1855 (Reel 1)
    - 1856-1859 (Reel 1)
  - Correspondence with Peter LeFevre
    - 1844-1847 (Reel 1)
    - 1848-1849 (Reel 1)
    - 1850-1855 (Reel 1)
  - Correspondence of the law firm of Wing and McClelland (later McClelland and Christiancy)
    - 1841-1844 (Reel 1)
    - 1845 (Reel 1)
    - 1846-1851 (Reel 1)
  - Letters from his children 1874-1875 (Reel 1)
- Business, financial, and miscellaneous
  - Land titles and deeds
    - 1835-1837 (Reel 1)
    - 1841-1849 (Reel 1)
    - 1850-1851 (Reel 1)
    - 1852-1856 undated (Reel 1)
  - Business Receipts (Reel 1)
  - Personal bills, receipts, and checks (Reel 1)
  - Letters concerning pending litigation 1831-1855 (Reel 1)
  - Architect's plans, bills, and receipts for his home (Reel 1)
  - Michigan Supreme Court docket July 1859 (Reel 1)
  - Address given May 21, 1861 at Monroe (Reel 1)
  - Certificates of election to the Supreme Court (Reel 1)
  - Diary and Memorandum book 1850 (Reel 1)
- Legal files: law practice and Michigan Supreme Court
  - Record of Court Cases 1846-1848 (Reel 2)
  - Cases
    - Peter Allan Estate (Reel 2)
    - Butler vs. Humphrey (Reel 2)
    - Creelman and Chapman vs. Farmington (Reel 2)
    - Culbertson vs. Damah (Reel 2)
    - Farmers and Mechanics Bank vs. Strong and Maer (Reel 2)
    - Farwell vs. Andrews (Reel 2)
    - Field vs. Christiancy (Reel 2)
    - Holman vs. Fort Wayne Railroad (Reel 2)
    - Miller vs. Arnold (Reel 2)
    - Nash vs. Filkins (Reel 2)
    - O'Connor vs. Murphy (Reel 2)
    - Francis Roberts Estate (Reel 2)
    - Shauvon vs. People of Michigan (Reel 2)
  - Miscellaneous briefs and complaints
    - 1839-1844 (Reel 2)
    - 1845-1849 (Reel 2)
    - 1850-1854 (Reel 2)
    - 1855-1857 (Reel 2)
    - Undated (Reel 2)
  - Miscellaneous legal materials and memoranda
    - 1800 (Reel 2)
    - 1830-1839 (Reel 2)
    - 1840-1844 (Reel 2)
    - 1845 (Reel 2)
    - 1846-1849 (Reel 2)
    - 1850-1851 (Reel 2)
    - 1852-1853 (Reel 2)
    - 1854-1859 (Reel 2)
    - 1860-1874 (Reel 2)
    - Undated (Reel 2)